Guide to the Henry Marie Brackenridge and Family Papers, 1816-1889 DAR.1937.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Henry Marie Brackenridge and Family Papers
1816-1889
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Brackenridge family
DAR.1937.03
1.67 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Henry Marie Brackenridge, eldest son of Hugh Henry Brackenridge, was a prominent statesman and writer involved in the politics of South America, Mexico, Louisiana, Florida, and Pennsylvania. The collection mainly focuses on correspondence concerning Henry Marie Brackenridge's political career. It contains letters from notable politicians of his day including Andrew Jackson, Henry Clay, John Quincy Adams, and William Henry Harrison, among others. Also included are letters to and from Brackenridge's wife, Caroline, as well as other family and friends, which provide a context for traveling, health, and life at that time. Digital reproductions of this collection are available online.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of this collection are available online.
Biography
Henry Marie Brackenridge was born on May 11, 1786, in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Brackenridge's varied career as a lawyer, judge and diplomat would take him to locations throughout the Western Hemisphere and led to contacts with many notable politicians of his day. Henry Marie's travels began early when his father, writer and judge, Hugh Henry Brackenridge, sent him to Louisiana to receive a French education. Taking after his father, Henry Marie pursued an education in law, eventually returning to his hometown to attend the Pittsburgh Academy. After gaining admittance to the bar in 1806, Brackenridge worked as a lawyer in Baltimore, Maryland; Somerset, Pennsylvania; and St. Louis, Missouri.
Brackenridge returned to Louisiana in 1811 as district attorney general for the Orleans Territory. When Louisiana entered the Union the following year, he helped shape the new state's legal code. During the War of 1812, Brackenridge provided intelligence to the Madison administration concerning developments in Louisiana. He later wrote a book on the subject, History of the Late War, between the United States and Great Britain, published in 1816.
In 1817, President James Monroe selected Brackenridge to participate in a fact-finding mission to South America, in order to report on the rebellious Spanish colonies. The Monroe administration hoped the mission would help decide the matter of whether or not to officially recognize any independent governments that should form after these conflicts. Brackenridge's resulting publication on the trip, Voyage of South America, Performed by Order of the American Government in the Years 1817 and 1818, expressed views largely in favor of the colonies establishing their independence. The work found an ardent supporter in Speaker of the House Henry Clay and explored ideas that are thought to have influenced what would later become known as the Monroe Doctrine.
Upon returning to the United States, Brackenridge was elected to the Maryland State Legislature. Along with another representative, he introduced a bill that would grant Jews the right to vote. The proposed legislation proved unpopular but revealed Brackenridge's belief in the importance of the separation between church and state.
A chance meeting with Andrew Jackson in 1821 led to Brackenridge's employment as the general's Spanish translator and secretary for a mission to the Florida territories. Through Jackson's influence, Brackenridge was appointed judge of West Florida. He presided over the region during its transition from a Spanish holding to a United States territory. In 1827, Brackenridge married Caroline Marie, a family friend whom he had known since childhood. The difficulties of frontier life and the potential for outbreaks of yellow fever kept the couple apart, with Caroline remaining in Pennsylvania while Brackenridge continued his tenure in Florida.
Following his dismissal as judge of West Florida in 1832, Brackenridge wrote a series of public letters criticizing the Jackson administration. Jackson responded, and the dispute continued in various newspaper editorials. Brackenridge argued that Jackson had replaced him with a political ally of the administration and accused the president of radically expanding the powers of the executive branch.
Brackenridge returned to Pennsylvania and settled into his wife's land near Pittsburgh, where the family established the towns of Natrona and Tarentum. In 1840, he was elected as a Whig to the United States Congress, replacing Richard Biddle. His attempt at re-nomination failed, but he was later elected to the Pennsylvania House of Representatives. Brackenridge continued to write and express his views until his death in 1871.
Scope and Content Notes
The focal point of this collection is the professional career of Henry Marie Brackenridge. There are also letters and documents written by and pertaining to the Brackenridge family. While the collection contains some published documents, approximately sixty-five percent of the papers consist of handwritten correspondence with Brackenridge. Also represented are some of Caroline Marie Brackenridge's personal papers and correspondence.
Henry Marie Brackenridge's professional correspondence encompasses letters from various notable contemporaries, including John Quincy Adams, Andrew Jackson, Henry Clay, and William Henry Harrison. The letters relate to Brackenridge's various professional activities, which took him to South America, Florida, and Washington, D.C. Other discussions cover controversial topics of the day, including America's role in the colonial wars of South America, corruption in the Jackson administration, and the legal status of slavery in newly admitted American states.
The Brackenridge family correspondence incorporates a number of letters between Henry Marie and Caroline, detailing the difficulties of their long separations. Letters from other family members are also represented, including Henry Marie's son, Benjamin Morgan, his brother, Alexander Brackenridge, and sister, Cornelia Brackenridge. All of these letters relate to some aspect of the Brackenridge family. Typically the letters address the health and well being of friends and family members. Education, attire, and careers are topics also covered within the correspondence. Family members writing to Henry Marie, especially Cornelia, often chided him for his lack of timely response to their letters, as well as for his long absences from home.
Henry Marie Brackenridge's speeches and essays contain drafts of various writings with handwritten corrections. Also included are newspaper clippings of articles by Brackenridge, along with editorial notes written in the margins. Items of note include copies of several speeches Brackenridge delivered at various Independence Day celebrations and a review of Uncle Tom's Cabin.
Miscellaneous items consist of obituaries, legal papers and handwritten copies of literary works by other authors. Researchers may be interested to note that three of Brackenridge's memorandum books are included in this series. The books contain notes that were clearly used in his published works detailing his work in Florida and criticisms of Andrew Jackson.
The locations of the sender and recipient have been noted when possible. Item level scope and content notes are provided for each folder in Series I, II, and III. Jane Honeycutt's dissertation on the letters of Henry Marie and Hugh Henry Brackenridge provided useful information in the creation of the notes as did the initial cataloging by the Darlington Memorial Library staff. The original catalog cards have been included in the folders when available. For matters of convenience, Brackenridge's name has been abbreviated to H. M. Brackenridge at the series level.
Arrangement
The order of these documents from the letter book has been noted through the inclusion of a letter book number (e.g. LB#01). See custodial history for more information. The collection is arranged into four series:
Series I. Henry Marie Brackenridge Professional Correspondence, 1817-1868
Series II. Brackenridge Family Correspondence, 1821-1857
Series III. Henry Marie Brackenridge Speeches and Essays, 1818-1864
Series IV. Miscellaneous Items, 1857-1889
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Darlington Memorial Library acquired the collection as gifts in 1937 and 1956.
Custodial History
The first gift mainly consisted of letters between Brackenridge and his wife, Caroline Marie. In 1956, Mrs. Helen Brackenridge Painter gave the University of Pittsburgh a letter book containing Henry Marie's political correspondence. This second gift housed approximately 130 items. The letter book was taken apart in 1970 and placed into individual folders. The two acquisitions were combined in 2006 to provide improved access to this comprehensive collection. Some of the correspondence was originally contained in a letter book, which was disbound by the Darlington Memorial staff upon its acquisition. The order of these documents from the letter book has been noted by the inclusion of a letter book number (e.g. LB#01).
This collection was located in the Darlington Memorial Library in the University's Cathedral of Learning until 2007 when it was moved to the ULS Archives Service Center for processing, storage, preservation and service. However, it remains in the custodianship of the ULS Special Collections Department.
Previous Citation
Henry Marie Brackenridge and Family Papers, 1816-1889, DAR.1937.03, Darlington Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Related Materials
Hugh Henry Brackenridge and Andrew Watson Papers, 1790-1827, DAR.1937.04, Darlington Collection, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Papers of the Brackenridge Family, 1796-1963, MSS #160, Historical Society of Western Pennsylvania
Bibliography
Honeycutt, Jane. "The Letters of H. M. and H. H. Brackenridge in the Pittsburgh Archives, 1796-1868." PhD diss., University of California Davis, 1986.
Keller, William F. The Nation's Advocate: Henry Marie Brackenridge and Young America. Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1956.
Judges -- Florida; Lawyers -- Pennsylvania; Pensacola (Fla.); Pittsburgh (Pa.); Natrona (Pa.); Tarentum (Pa.); Brackenridge (Pa.); United States -- History -- War of 1812; United States -- Territories and possessions; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1775-1865; Maryland -- Politics and government -- 1775-1865; Florida -- Politics and government -- 1821-1865; Louisiana -- Politics and government -- 1803-1865; United States -- Politics and government -- 19th century; Lawyers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Missouri compromise; Diplomats -- South America; Brackenridge, Benjamin Morgan; Brackenridge, Caroline Marie; Brackenridge family; Brackenridge, Cornelia; Brackenridge, H. H. (Hugh Henry); Brackenridge, H. M. (Henry Marie)
- Henry Marie Brackenridge, Professional Correspondence, 1817-1868; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The majority of the letters contained in this series were written to Henry Marie Brackenridge (H. M. Brackenridge). Most of the correspondence addressed to him conveys details of his professional career as secretary to a mission to South America, commissioner on the Mexican Claims Commission, judge in the territory of West Florida, U.S. Representative, and author. His book, Voyage of South America, Performed by Order of the American Government in the Years 1817 and 1818, is a recurring topic. The letters also discuss many of the historical events of the time such as the Missouri Compromise, Florida's transition from a Spanish holding to a US territory, Peru's fight for independence from Spain, and other political struggles in South America.
  Arrangement
  The letters are arranged in chronological order. The order of these documents from the letter book has been noted by the inclusion of a letter book number (e.g. LB#01). See custodial history for more information.
  - Walter Forward to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 90), September 24, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Forward, writing from Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, to Baltimore, Maryland, sends news of several people, including his brother Chauncey. Forward notes his lack of ambition and dissatisfaction with his work. 3 p. A.L.S.
  - James Ross to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 94), February 15, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Ross, writing from Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, to Baltimore, Maryland replies to H. M. Brackenridge concerning an edition of Modern Chivalry by Hugh Henry Brackenridge. 1 p. A.L.S.
  - Richard Rush to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 22), May 6, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Rush, writing from Washington, D.C., encloses his pamphlet on jurisprudence. He reflects on the value of his friendship with the late Hugh Henry Brackenridge. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Richard Rush to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 21), July 17, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Rush, writing from Washington, D.C., relays James Monroe's desire to send H. M. Brackenridge to South America as secretary of a commission. 3 p. A.L.S.
  - E.S. Sergeant to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 13), July 22, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Sergeant, writing from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Baltimore, Maryland, discusses legal matters. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - John Graham to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 10), July 29, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Writting from Washington, D.C., Graham describes preparations for the trip to South America. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Richard Rush to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 117), July 30, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    From Washington, D.C, Rush covers matters related to H. M. Brackenridge's upcoming trip to South America. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - James Biddle to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 99), October 3, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Biddle, writing from the U.S. Sloop, which traveled from Ontario, New York to Baltimore, Maryland, informs H. M. Brackenridge of the whereabouts of his provisions for the trip to South America. He also expresses regret at not being able to accompany the mission, as was originally planned. 1 p. A.L.S.
  - David Porter to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 32), October 26, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Porter, writing from Washington, D.C., explains how his opinions on South America are similar to those of H. M. Brackenridge. He suggests that they meet to discuss these matters further. 3 p. A.L.S.
  - Henry Clay to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 120), August 4, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Clay, writing from Lexington, Kentucky, to Wilmington, Delaware, makes note of his interest in the findings of the commission, of which H. M. Brackenridge was a member. Clay also reveals he published H. M. Brackenridge's letter from Buenos Aires, as he considered it something "proper for the public to see." 3 p. A.L.S.
  - Henry Clay to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 123), August 18, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Clay, writing from Lexington, Kentucky, to Wilmington, Delaware, asks whether or not the commission has submitted a final report to the government. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Abbé José Francisco Correa da Serra to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 85), October 12, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Correa da Serra, writing from Washington, D.C., to Baltimore, Maryland, notes his desire to hire H.M. Brackenridge in a legal capacity. 1 p. A.L.S.
  - John Young to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 106), January 13, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Young, writing from Greensburg, Pennsylvania, to Annapolis, Maryland, conveys his opposition to the "Jew Bill" before the Maryland legislature. The measure, which H.M. Brackenridge supports, aims to increase the rights of Maryland residents of the Jewish faith. 3 p. A.L.S.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to John Young (LB # 130), January 22, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    From Annapolis, Maryland, H.M. Brackenridge replies to Young's letter concerning the "Jew Bill." H.M. Brackenridge outlines his belief in the right to worship freely. He also offers his opinion on religion in South America. 3 p. A.L.S.
  - Caesar Augustus Rodney to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 50), April 4, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Rodney, writing from Wilmington, Delaware, to Baltimore, Maryland, discusses H.M. Brackenridge's proposed book on the mission to South America. 1 p. A.L.S.
  - George Reinholdt to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 73), April 14, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Reinholdt, writing from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Baltimore, Maryland, wants to discuss the sale of land. He also gives assurances that he gave Mr. Sergeant the letter H.M. Brackenridge requested he courier. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - William Shaler to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 91), July 5, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Shaler, writing from the U.S.S. Nanklin Gibraltar, states he is eagerly awaiting H.M. Brackenridge's book on the mission to South America. He also describes the various troubles concerning life at sea. 3 p. A.L.S.
  - Caesar Augustus Rodney to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 36), July 25, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Rodney, writing from Wilmington, Delaware, to Baltimore, Maryland, praises H.M. Brackenridge's book. He suggests H.M. Brackenridge should consider becoming District Attorney of Baltimore. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Peter Stephen DuPonceau to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 30), August 7, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    DuPonceau, writing from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, perhaps erroneously addresses this letter to "H.H. Brackenridge" (Hugh Henry Brackenridge). The letter reflects on H.M. Brackenridge's book on South America. 1 p. A.L.S.
  - William P. Brobson to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 16), August 14, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Brobson, writing from Wilmington, Delaware, to Baltimore, Maryland, discusses South American affairs and H.M. Brackenridge's book. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Henry Clay to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 86), August 28, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Clay, writing from Lexington, Kentucky, to Baltimore, Maryland, outlines his thoughts about the independence movement in South America and H.M. Brackenridge's writings on the area. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - W. Pinkney Jr.to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 88), September 12, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Pinkney, writing from Baltimore, Maryland, asks about assuming command of H.M. Brackenridge's military company. 1 p. A.L.S.
  - Stephen Pleasonton to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 33), October 27, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Writing from Washington, D.C., to Baltimore, Maryland, Pleasonton thanks H.M. Brackenridge for some books that were sent to the President. 1 p. A.L.S.
  - David Hoffman to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 110), November 15, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Hoffman, writing from Baltimore, Maryland, invites H.M. Brackenridge to join a literary group. He also includes a list of the other proposed members. 1 p. A.L.S.
  - James Parton to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 128), November 28, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Parton, writing from New York City, New York, thanks H.M. Brackenridge for a letter of praise for one of his works. 3 p. A.L.S.
  - Henry Clay to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 122), March 7, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Clay, writing from Washington, D.C., to Baltimore, Maryland, comments on Spain, Buenos Aires, and the Missouri Compromise. 1 p. A.L.S.
  - William T. Read to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 80), March 17, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Read, writing from New Castle, Delaware, refutes criticisms of H.M. Brackenridge related to the mission to South America. 4 p. A.L.S.
  - Caesar Augustus Rodney to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 23), May 18, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Rodney, writing from Wilmington, Delaware, to Baltimore, Maryland, compliments H.M. Brackenridge on his book about South America. He also comments on the political situation in South America and Henry Clay. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Caesar Augustus Rodney to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 39), July 2, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Rodney, writing from Wilmington, Delaware, to Baltimore, Maryland, notes his intent to visit Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson. 1 p. A.L.S.
  - Richard Rush to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 95), December 4, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Rush, writing from London, England, praises H.M. Brackenridge's book. 3 p. A.L.S.
  - Thomas Hart Benton to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 92), January 30, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Writing from Washington, D.C., Benton discusses the admittance of Missouri to the Union. The letter also references efforts to establish relations with China, Japan, and the Indian Archipelago. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - John Scott to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 17), February 8, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Scott, writing from Washington, D.C., outlines the legal implications of the Missouri Compromise. 3 p. A.L.S.
  - Thomas Hart Benton to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 48), March 1, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Writing from Washington, D.C., Benton asks H.M. Brackenridge to write some pieces in support of the resolution for the admission of Missouri into the Union. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - James C. Bronaugh to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 09), undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    H.M. Brackenridge received this letter in Pensacola, Florida. Only a partial letter exists, and it is not clear from where it was sent. Bronaugh writes of plans to visit Florida and congratulates H.M. Brackenridge on his appointment. 1 p. A.L.
  - Andrew Jackson to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 51), July 8, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Jackson, writing from Manuels (state unknown), to Pensacola, Florida, discusses property records and a disagreement he had with "the Governor." 2 p. A.L.S.
  - G. W. Alvares to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 105), October 14, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Alvares, writing from Buenos Aires, to Baltimore, Maryland, describes the war in Peru for independence from Spain. The letter is written in Spanish. 3 p. A.L.S.
  - John Caldwell Calhoun to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 78), October 23, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Writing from Washington, D.C., Calhoun comments on H.M. Brackenridge's book and the political direction of South America. 4 p. A.L.S.
  - James Gadsden to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 08), January 23, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Gadsden, writing from Washington, D.C., to Pensacola, Florida, responds to a letter H.M. Brackenridge addressed to President Monroe concerning an attack on a civilian by an army officer in West Florida. 1 p. A.L.S.
  - John Quincy Adams to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 79), June 11, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    John Quincy Adams, writing from Washington, D. C., to Pensacola, Florida, appoints H.M. Brackenridge as judge of West Florida. Also enclosed is a commission for Benjamin Robertson to become United States Marshal. 1 p. L.S.
  - William Sebree to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 72), February 6, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Sebree, writing from Georgetown, Kentucky, to Pensacola, Florida, announces his appointment as United States Marshal for West Florida. 1 p. A.L.S.
  - H. M. Brackenridge letter draft (LB # 61), September 12, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    In this draft, H.M. Brackenridge requests descriptions of the South Carolina and Georgia coastlines, in order to compare them with those in Florida. The last part of draft seems to be missing. 4 p. unsigned
  - John Quincy Adams to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 93), January 8, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Adams, writing from Washington, D.C., to Pensacola, Florida, encloses H.M. Brackenridge's commission as Judge of West Florida and expresses regrets that it had been so long delayed. 1 p. L.S.
  - James Gadsden to H.M. Brackenridge (LB# 71), January 7, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Gadsden, writing from Tallahassee, Florida, lays down his principles for the constitution of the Florida Institute of Agriculture, Antiquities and Science, which is referred to in the letter below. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - James Gadsden to H. M. Brackenridge (LB# 104), January 12, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 44)